[Music]
foreign
in 2010 the first control draw was
published examining how the brain
responds to grape juice it helped aged
rats but what about people concord grape
juice supplementation improves memory
function in older adults with mild
cognitive impairment or so says the
title the problem is that the study was
funded by Welches and though the authors
claim they have no financial interest in
the outcome that seems disingenuous I
mean do you think Welches would you know
ever fund them again if they found the
you know grape juice wasn't good for you
and indeed that title is a bit of
Industry spin I mean I'm sure that's
what they wanted to find older adults
with memory decline but not dementia
were randomized into a
placebo-controlled double-blind trial
with concord grape juice versus uh same
calorie same sugar similarly looking
tasting grape Kool-Aid type drink so
that's a solid study design and look
berries have those wonderful polyphenol
phytonutrients which you know have
anti-inflammatory and antioxidant
properties so it certainly could help
brain function and it did seem to help
with verbal learning the chances you'd
get such a notable result just by chance
is like 1 in 25. where is the higher
recall scores are considered not
statistically significant since even if
there wasn't an effect you might get
those kind of results by chance one in
every you know eight or ten times you'd
run the experiment and by convention we
really like to see at least one in 20.
so a p-value of 0.05 or less especially
if you're looking at multiple outcomes
which increases the likelihood that
something will you know just kind of pop
up as a fluke bottom line is that we're
less confident in those kind of memory
outcomes so I imagine if this hadn't had
industry funding it would have been
titled more accurately you know concord
grape juice supplementation improves
verbal learning in older adults with
mild cognitive impairment which is still
an important finding and you know we
have the Welch's Corporation to thank
for it and without industry funding a
study like this you know it might never
get done
the findings suggests that drinking
grape juice is superior to drinking
grape Kool-Aid not necessarily for
memory but uh you know maybe for helping
with learning when the study was
repeated though it did seem to help one
measure of memory but found no benefit
for verbal learning even when using the
exact same test as before which you know
calls the previous results into question
so we're left you know uncertain about
what effects if any grape juice has on
the Aging brain
what about the brains of middle-aged
mothers the Welch's funded researchers
noted significant improvements in one
measure of memory and driving
performances measured in some fancy
driving simulator suggesting on grape
juice you might be able to stop a dozen
yards earlier on the highway than if you
had instead been drinking grape Kool-Aid
man I do like how they tried to like
translate the cognitive effects into
more you know meaningful metrics but you
know it's important to acknowledge as
they did that you know no effects were
found for the majority of cognitive
consequences and and when you study you
know 20 different outcomes the odds are
pretty good you're just gonna get a
statistically significant result or two
by chance
the latest study uh involved a single
dose given to young adults average age
21 a cup of purple grape juice or white
grape juice to which flavor and color
had been added to disguise it in this
way you could see if there's something
special about those Deep Purple
polyphenol pigments in concord grape
juice and got the same kind of results
uh two cognitive measures just reaching
statistical significance but you know
that's out of seven different outcomes
so instead of
0.05 was the cutoff for significance
we'd really like to see closer to
.007 and none hit that uh maybe it's
because they didn't use the whole food
like in that blueberry study I profiled
before there was a study that looked at
actual grape consumption by utilizing
freeze-dried grape powder to capture the
you know kind of Whole Food instead of
just the juice versus a sugar matched
Placebo they used pet scans to track
changes in brain metabolism associated
with early Alzheimer's and a group of
older adults already suffering from mild
cognitive decline although the changes
couldn't be picked up on neuropsych
testing in those early stage Alzheimer's
regions the placebo group continued to
worsen but the grape group was spared
such decline suggesting a protective
effect of grapes here's that in kind of
graph form showing the significant
differences or even better brain mapping
pictures right here's one of the placebo
brains the red areas indicate locations
where your brain metabolism declined
after six months of eating Placebo
grapes compare that level of decline to
a brain that ate six months of actual
grapes
foreign